1 Peter 3:18–22
God’s longsuffering lasted 120 years, the time Noah built the ark.
Throughout that time, God waited for people to turn away from their idolatry and go to themselves.
But that didn't happen.
In the third chapter of his first epistle from verse 18 onwards, the Apostle Peter writes:
For Christ also hath once suffered for sins,
the just for the unjust,
that he might bring us to God,
being put to death in the flesh, but quickened by the Spirit:
By which also he went and preached unto the spirits in prison;
Which sometime were disobedient, when once the longsuffering of God waited in the days of Noah,
while the ark was a preparing, wherein few, that is, eight souls were saved by water.
It is noteworthy to what Peter compares baptism.
He has spoken only a moment before about a situation in which a Christian may have to suffer blame for the name of Christ.
But that is not the main thing for Peter.
He specifically chooses from the Old Testament a context by which he can comfort a Christian who suffers from it.
By choosing the subject of the days of Noah, Peter wants to talk about baptism.
Just as God saved eight souls in the ark.
They were on the water and all their enemies were wiped off the face of the earth.
They themselves did not participate in any way other than simply accept what happened.
God executed the judgment,
God decided to save those eight people in a very safe way for them.
Those eight in the ark had absolutely nothing to worry about.
As long as they remained inside the ark, for what happened outside the ark had no power over them.
They are completely safe under God's protection.
Peter continues:
The like figure whereunto even baptism doth also now save us
— That's us!
not the putting away of the filth of the flesh, but the answer of a good conscience toward God,
by the resurrection of Jesus Christ:
There are many things here.
So baptism is something that is not deeds where a person would do something by themselves to be saved.
It's not about a rite. It's not about putting away of the filth of the flesh.
It is not in the outwardly glory.
But as little as Noah and the seven other who were with him in the ark.
They had more or less nothing to do with being saved from the flood.
In the same way, we Christians have next to nothing to do with our baptism destroying everything which doesn't fit into the kingdom of heaven.
Its reference point is the flood.
A body of water that wipes away everything as it goes away.
It can be compared to any act of your own that you could try,
it is a mass of water that cannot be resisted.
It simply wipes it all out,
makes dead what needs to die.
After all, when God waited for 120 years in the days of Noah,
this could have ended at least in theory in the same way as with Jonah in Nineveh.
That the people would turn to God,
the people would go to themselves and cry out to God for help.
That they would find that they are not on the right path and the only one who can help them is the LORD Himself.
But that was not the case with Noah.
The reason Peter chooses the flood is that he wants to write as clearly as possible
how mighty and powerful baptism actually is.
In it we are baptized into the death of Christ.
That is not a trivial matter.
In it we are clothed in the good merits of Christ, in his life, and in the righteousness we have received as a gift from Him.
It can be despised in the same way the people looked down the longsuffering of God for 120 years in the days of Noah.
But that has a terrible outcome.
Because then the same would happen as for those in ancient times
to the disobedient spirits to whom Christ preached after descending to hell.
It was no happy sermon.
They were guaranteed to be full of horror.
But this text focuses specifically on this primarily: What does God do?
The like figure
whereunto even baptism doth also now save us
not the putting away of the filth of the flesh,
So it is not about good deeds.
It's not about relying on your own works, it's not about improving your own life
in order to please God.
Of course it happens that when the grace has been clarified
the walk of life will change externally as well.
In some it is more visible than in the others.
But nevertheless: it’s not about your own deeds,
but the answer of a good conscience toward God,
by the resurrection of Jesus Christ:
A good conscience and baptism essentially belong together.
The like figure whereunto even baptism doth also now save us
not the putting away of the filth of the flesh, but the answer of a good conscience toward God, by the resurrection of Jesus Christ:
Who is gone into heaven, and is on the right hand of God;
angels and authorities and powers being made subject unto him.